The most complex problems in our time
أكثر المشاكل تعقيدا في عصرنا
can be solved with simple techniques,
يمكن حلها بتقنيات بسيطة،
if we are able to dream.
إذا ما استطعنا أن نحلم.
As a child, I discovered that creativity is the key
عندما كنت طفلا، اكتشفت أن الإبداع هو مفتاح
to cross from dreams to reality.
العبور من الأحلام إلى الواقع.
I learned this from my grandmother,
تعلمت هذا من جدتي،
Dr. Ruth Tichauer,
الدكتورة روث تيتشاور،
a Jewish refugee that settled in the heart of the Andes.
لاجئة يهودية استقرت في قلب جبال الأنديز.
That is how I grew up:
هكذا ترعرعت:
encouraged to see beyond any limitation.
لقد تم تشجيعي لرؤية ما وراء الحدود.
So part of my education included helping her
لذا جزء تعليمي شمل مساعدتها
in remote, indigenous communities.
في مجتمعات نائية، للسكان الأصليين.
I cherish those memories,
أنا أعتز بتلك الذكريات،
because they helped me to understand life outside the city,
لأنها ساعدتني على فهم الحياة خارج المدينة،
a life with a lot of possibilities,
حياة مليئة بكثير من الاحتمالات،
without barriers, as language or culture.
من دون حواجز، كاللغة أو الثقافة.
During those trips, my grandmother used to recite a Kipling poem:
خلال تلك الرحلات، كانت جدتي تُلقي قصيدة كبلنغ:
"Something hidden. Go and find it.
"شيء ما مخفي .اذهب واعثر عليه.
Go and look behind the Mountains.
اذهب وابحث وراء الجبال.
Something lost behind the mountains.
شيء ما مفقود وراء الجبال.
Lost and waiting for you. Go!"
مفقود وفي انتظارك. اذهب!"
In the coming years, I became a medical student.
في السنوات المقبلة، أصبحت طالبا في كلية الطب.
One of every hundred children born worldwide
واحد من كل مائة طفل مولود في جميع أنحاء العالم
has some kind of heart disease.
لديه نوع من أمراض القلب.
There's a part of this problem I think I can solve --
هناك جزء من هذه المشكلة أعتقد أنني أستطيع حله -
the part of this problem I have spent my life working on.
الجزء الذي قضيت حياتي في العمل على حله.
The problem starts
تبدأ المشكلة
during pregnancy.
خلال فترة الحمل.
The fetus needs to survive inside the mother.
يحتاج الجنين إلى البقاء على قيد الحياة داخل الأم.
Survival depends on communication
يعتمد البقاء على قيد الحياة على التواصل
between the systemic and the pulmonary blood.
بين ما هو نظامي والدم الرئوي.
At the moment of birth,
في لحظة الولادة،
this communication needs to stop.
يحتاج هذا التواصل للتوقف.
If it doesn't close, the baby has a hole in the heart.
إذا لم يغلق، يصبح لدى الطفل ثقب في القلب.
It is caused by prematurity and genetic conditions.
وهو ناتج عن الولادة المبكرة والأمراض الوراثية.
But what we know today
ولكن ما نعرفه اليوم
is that a lack of oxygen is also one of the causes.
هو أن نقص الأكسجين هو أيضا أحد المسببات.
As you can see in the chart,
كما ترون في الرسم البياني،
the frequency of this kind of hole
فإن تواتر هذا النوع من الثقوب
dramatically increases with altitude.
يزيد بشكل كبير مع الارتفاع.
Video: (Baby crying)
فيديو: (طفل يبكي)
When you look at patients with this condition,
عند النظر إلى المرضى الذين يعانون من هذه الحالة،
they seem desperate to breathe.
فإنهم يبدوون في حاجة ماسة للتنفس.
To close the hole, major surgery used to be the only solution.
لإغلاق الثقب، كان الحل الوحيد هوعملية جراحية كبرى.
One night, my friend Malte, were camping in the Amazon region.
في إحدى الليالي، كنا أنا وصديقي مالتي، نقوم بالتخييم في منطقة الأمازون.
The only thing that would not burn in the fire was a green avocado branch.
وكان الشيء الوحيد الذي لم يُحرق في النار هو فرع أفوكادو أخضر.
Then came a moment of inspiration.
ثم جاءت لحظة إلهام.
So we used the branch as a mold for our first invention.
لذا استخدمنا ذلك الفرع كقالب لأول اختراع لنا.
The holes in children's hearts can be closed with it.
يمكن استخدامه لإغلاق تلك الثقوب في قلوب الأطفال.
A coil is a piece of wire wrapped onto itself.
اللفافة هي قطعة من الأسلاك ملفوفة حول نفسها.
It maybe doesn't look so fancy to you now,
ربما قد لا تبدو راقية جدا لكم الآن،
but that was our first successful attempt
ولكن تلك كانت أول محاولة ناجحة لنا
to create a device for this major problem.
لإنشاء جهاز لهذه المشكلة الكبيرة.
In this video, we can see how a very tiny catheter
في هذا الفيديو، يمكننا أن نرى كيف أن قسطرة صغيرة جدا
takes the coil to the heart.
تأخذ اللفافة إلى القلب.
The coil then closes the hole.
وعندها تقوم اللفافة بإغلاق الثقب.
After that moment of inspiration,
بعد تلك اللحظة من الإلهام،
there came a very long time of effort
جاء وقت طويل جدا من الجهد
developing a prototype.
لتطوير نموذج أولي.
In vitro and in vivo studies took thousands of hours of work in the lab.
استغرقت الدراسات المجراة في المختبر وفي الوسط الحيوي آلاف الساعات من العمل .
The coil, if it works, can save lives.
إن اللفافة ، إذا عملت، يمكن أن تنقذ أرواحا.
I returned from Germany to Bolivia,
عدت من ألمانيا إلى بوليفيا،
thinking that wherever we go,
معتقدا أنه وأينما ذهبنا،
we have the opportunity to make a difference.
فإننا نملك فرصة لإحداث فرق ما.
With my wife and partner, Dr. Alexandra Heath,
أنا وزوجتي وشريكتي، الدكتورة ألكسندرا هيث،
we started to see patients.
بدأنا نرى المرضى.
After successfully treating patients with our coil,
بعد علاج المرضى بنجاح باستخذام اللفائف خاصتنا،
we felt really enthusiastic.
شعرنا بحماس قوي.
But we live in a place
لكننا نعيش في مكان
that is 12,000 feet high.
مرتفع ب12،000 قدم،
And,
و
the patients there need a special device to solve their heart condition.
المرضى هناك في حاجة إلى جهاز خاص لمعالجة حالة قلوبهم.
The hole in altitude patients is different,
ارتفاع الثقب لدى المرضى مختلف،
because the orifice between the arteries is larger.
لأن الفتحة بين الشرايين أوسع.
Most patients cannot afford to be treated on time,
ليس باستطاعة معظم المرضى أن يتعالجوا في الوقت المناسب،
and they die.
وكانوا يموتون.
The first coil could successfully treat
إن اللفافة الأولى تمكنت أن تعالج بنجاح
only half of the patients in Bolivia.
نصف المرضى في بوليفيا فقط.
The search started again.
بدأ البحث مرة أخرى.
We went back to the drawing board.
عدنا إلى لوحة الرسم.
After many trials,
بعد العديد من التجارب،
and with the help of my grandmother's indigenous friends in the mountains,
وبمساعدة من أصدقاء جدتي من السكان الأصليين في الجبال،
we obtained a new device.
حصلنا على جهاز جديد.
For centuries, indigenous women told stories by weaving complex patterns
لعدة قرون، روت نساء الشعوب الأصلية قصصا عبر نسج أنماط معقدة
on looms,
على النول،
and an unexpected skill helped us for the new device.
ومهارة غير متوقعة ساعدتنا في الجهاز الجديد.
We take this traditional method of weaving
قمنا بأخذ هذه الطريقة التقليدية في الحياكة
and make a design made by a smart material
وصنعنا تصميما معمول بمادة ذكية
that records shape.
والذي يُسجل الشكل.
It seems this time,
يبدو هذه المرة،
the weaving allows us to create a seamless device
أن النسيج يسمح لنا بإنشاء جهاز سلس
that doesn't rust
لا يصدأ
because it's made of only one piece.
لأنه مصنوع من قطعة واحدة فقط.
It can change by itself into very complex structures
ويمكن له أن يتغير من تلقاء نفسه إلى هياكل معقدة جدا
by a procedure that took decades to develop.
عبر إجراء استغرق عقودا ليتطور.
As you can see, the device enters the body
كما ترون، فإن الجهاز يدخل إلى الجسم
through the natural channels.
عبر القنوات الطبيعية.
Doctors have only to close the catheter through the hole.
كل ما يقوم به الأطباء هو إغلاق القسطرة عبر الثقب.
Our device expands, places itself
يتمدد جهازنا ، يتموقع
and closes the hole.
ويغلق الثقب.
We have this beautiful delivery system
لدينا نظام تسليم جميل
that is so simple to use
وهو بغاية السهولة للإستخدام
because it works by itself.
لأنه يعمل من تلقاء نفسه.
No open surgery was necessary.
لا حاجة لعملية جراحية مفتوحة .
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
As doctors, we fight with diseases
نحن كأطباء، نقاتل ضد الأمراض
that take a long time and effort to heal -- if they do.
التي تستغرق وقتا طويلا وجهدا للشفاء - إذا ما حدث ذلك.
This is the child from before,
هذا هو الطفل الذي رأيناه من قبل،
after the procedure.
بعد العملية.
As you can see --
كما ترون -
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
As you can see, once the device is in place,
كما ترون، وبمجرد أن يتمركز الجهاز في مكانه،
the patient is 100 percent healed.
فإن المريض يُشفى بنسبة 100 في المئة.
From start to finish,
من البداية إلى النهاية،
the whole procedure takes only 30 minutes.
لايأخذ الإجراء بأكمله سوى 30 دقيقة.
That's very rewarding from the medical and human point of view.
هذا أمر مجزِ للغاية من وجهة النظر الطبية والإنسانية.
We are so proud that some of our former patients
نحن فخورون جدا لكون بعض المرضى السابقين لدينا
are part of our team --
جزءً من فريقنا -
a team, thanks to added close interaction
فريق، بفضل التفاعل الوثيق
with patients that work with us.
مع المرضى الذين يعملون معنا.
Together, we have only one idea:
معا، لدينا فكرة واحدة فقط:
the best solutions need to be simple.
أفضل الحلول يجب أن تكون بسيطة.
We lost the fear of creating something new.
لقد فقدنا الخوف من صنع شيء جديد.
The path, it's not easy.
الطريق ليس سهلا.
Many obstacles arise all the time.
تنشأ العديد من العقبات في كل وقت.
But we receive strength from our patients.
لكننا نتلقى القوة من مرضانا.
Their resilience and courage
مرونتهم وشجاعتهم
inspire our creativity.
تلهم إبداعنا.
Our goal is to make sure
إن هدفنا هو التأكد
that no child is left behind,
من عدم إقصاء أي طفل ،
not because of cost or access.
بسبب التكلفة أو التوفر.
So we have to start a foundation
لذلك علينا أن نبدأ مؤسسة
with a one-to-one model.
ذات نموذج شخصي.
We will give one device for free
سنمنح جهازا واحدا مجانا
to make sure that every child is treated.
للتأكد من معالجة كل طفل.
We are in many countries now,
نحن نتواجد في الكثير من البلدان الآن،
but we need to be everywhere.
ولكننا بحاجة إلى التواجد في كل مكان.
This whole thing began
لقد بدأ هذا الأمر كله
with one impossible idea
مع فكرة مستحيلة واحدة
as will continue it, really:
كما ستستمر في ذلك، فعلا:
No child is left behind.
لا إقصاء لأي طفل.
Muchas gracias.
شكرا جزيلا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)